Today with the last פרק perek. *perek* of בכורות *Bechorot*, מעשר בהמה
Maaser Behema. *Ma'aser Behema*, and it's been a very fun מסכת masechet,
*masechet* and we still have about a week to go. Now this,
now that we've done with talking about פדיון הבן *Pidyon HaBen* and
we've talked about the status of a בכור bechor. *bechor* for inheritance
as well, of which there is a lot more material in בבא
בתרא *Bava Batra* which deals with the laws of inheritance. We go
to the last chapter which deals with מעשר בהמה ma'asar behema, *Ma'aser
Behema*. What does מעשר בהמה ma'asar behema *Ma'aser Behema* have to do
with a בכור bechor? *bechor*? Why is it here? So תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* says that very often the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* speaks and the
משנה mishnah *Mishnah* speaks about a triad which is מעשר maaser. *Ma'aser*,
בכור bechor *Bechor*, and קרבן korban פסח *Korban Pesach*, because all of
those three are similar in the way they're brought in the בית
המקדש Beis Ha-mikdash. *Beit HaMikdash* in terms of what you do with
the דם *dam* and how you bring them and so on. I
think more simply, and then פסח *Pesach* of course has its own
מסכת *masechet*. I think more simply, it's that בכור bechor. *bechor* and
מעשר maaser *ma'aser* are unique in that they, in that when
they get a blemish, I mean particularly the way it applies nowadays.
That number one, you can't control that בכור bechor. *bechor* applies nowadays,
how you're going to deal with that. מעשר maaser *Ma'aser* you're supposed
to give, you're supposed to count and designate, although we'll talk about
that in a minute. And number two is that it's not irrelevant
to talk about them applying nowadays because they are the only קרבנות
Korbanos. *korbanot* that can be eaten with a blemish outside the בית
המקדש Beis Ha-mikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. Normally if something gets a blemish, you
redeem it and then you use the money in the future to
buy a קרבן korban, *korban*. But these actually have laws about how
you eat this קרבן korban, *korban* outside the בית המקדש Beis Ha-mikdash?
*Beit HaMikdash* when they have a blemish. So in that way I
think that it's for that purpose that it's put here in מסכת
בכורות *Masechet Bechorot* because it really is almost identical to a בכור
bechor? *bechor* with the one exception that the בכור bechor *bechor* you
give to a כהן Kohen. *kohen* and the מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser*, and
he brings it as a קרבן Korban *korban* and if he can't
bring it as a קרבן Korban. *korban* he eats it with a
blemish, and the מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser*, if you can't bring it as
a קרבן korban *korban* because it has a blemish, then you eat
it out of the בית המקדש Beis Ha-mikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. But both
of them are similar in that they're eaten with a blemish outside
of the בית המקדש Beis Ha-mikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*. So now let's take
a look at the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* at the beginning of the
פרק *perek*. נ"ג עמוד א' *Nun Gimmel Amud Aleph*. Yes.
Just to clarify that you had to bring it
to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beit HaMikdash* as a קרבן korban.
*korban*, right.
Even though it has a מום mum. *mum*?
No, I'm sorry, no. With a מום mum, *mum*, you eat it
outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash*.
Same way a בכור bechor *bechor*. And eating outside means anywhere?
Anywhere, anywhere you want. בשעריך תאכלנו *Bish'arecha tochelenu*. New Jersey. Exactly.
It doesn't have to be ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*, it could be Tel
Aviv, it could be אילת *Eilat*, it could presumably be Newark, it
could be anywhere with a מום mum, *mum* outside of the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*.
And that counts?
Yes,
it doesn't count as a קרבן korban? *korban* but the point is
it still has קדושת קרבן korban, *kedushat korban* and that restricts what
you do with it with a מום mum *mum*. For example, while
you can eat it and while a טמא *tamei* person can eat
it and so on, you cannot shear it, you cannot work it.
The only thing you're allowed to do while it's alive, the only
thing you're allowed to do is slaughter it and eat it. So
it is, מעשר ma'aser *Ma'aser* and בכור bechor, *Bechor* are unique in
this way, that the blemish is not what allows them to be
redeemed, but the blemish, that they can even be eaten with their
blemish although the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* is still on it. But that
קדושה kedusha *kedusha* now does not require once it has a blemish
to be brought as a קרבן korban. *korban*, that קדושה kedusha *kedusha*
is direct, you know, sort of is expressed in the fact that
you can't do anything other than שחט shecht *shecht* it and eat
it. Yeah, okay.
And so different than any other animal?
Right. For sure, because other animals you can work and shear and
so on, right. Okay.
And they're mentioned together in that chapter in זבחים *Zevachim*, they're in
the קרבנות Korbanos *korbanot* of the same.
Right, הבכור והמעשר והפסח *HaBechor veHaMa'aser veHaPesach*. So that's what תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafot* says and he focuses on the fact that the way the
דם *dam* was done was the same. But I think more interesting
than that is what's really distinctive about them is this idea that
with a blemish you don't redeem it, you eat it with a
blemish with the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* out of the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*. Okay, so let's take a look now at the
first at the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*. נ"ג עמוד א' *Nun Gimmel Amud
Aleph*. מעשר בהמה ma'asar behema. *Ma'aser Behema*, the מעשר בהמה ma'asar behema
*Ma'aser Behema*, נוהג noheg בארץ ובחוצה לארץ *noheg ba'aretz u'v'chutz la'aretz*. You're
familiar with this structure of the משנה *Mishnah* because we had it
at the last, you know, about half of the chapters in חולין
*Chullin*. Okay, it applies in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael* and
in חוצה לארץ Chutza La'aretz. *Chutz La'Aretz*. Why not? The תורה Torah
*Torah* says you have to give מעשר ma'aser. *Ma'aser*, so if it
doesn't have a blemish you would bring it up to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash* and eat it there. בפני הבית ושלא
בפני הבית Bifnei habayis v'shelo bifnei habayis, *Bifnei habayit veshelo bifnei habayit*,
whether there's a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash* or not. Obviously
you're not going to bring it as a קרבן korban *korban* without,
but you still have an obligation to sanctify it and then deal
with the consequences, we'll talk about that. בחולין אבל לא במוקדשין *Bechullin
aval lo bemukdashin*, in non-sanctified animals but not in previously sanctified ones,
like of course not, they're already sanctified and they're not yours, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will talk about all of that. Fine. ונוהג
בבקר ובצאן *Venoheg babakar u'vatzon*, and it applies in cattle and in
sheep, in the flock I should say. ואין מתעשרין מזה על זה
ve'ein misasrin mizeh al zeh, *Ve'ein mit'asrin mizeh al zeh*. You cannot
take מעשר ma'aser *Ma'aser*, now the way it applies is all the
new animals that are born each year. The ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
*Rosh Hashanah* for מעשר בהמה Maiser Beheima *Ma'aser Behema* is ראש חודש
אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul, *Rosh Chodesh Elul*, by the way. It's in
one of the ארבעה ראשי שנים הם *arba'ah rashei hashanim hem*. It's
for when animals, it's when the animals, it's like when the new
season for animals begin. The animals, like the same way
the ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* for crops is תשרי *Tishrei*. Why? It
starts a new season when the animals will become impregnated and starting
giving birth again, but it's not like humans, you know, where it
can be any time during the year. There are particular seasons in
which primarily animals are giving birth. So anyway, so so the every
animal that's born in the new year from last ראש חודש אלול
Rosh Chodesh Elul, to this one, you put them all into a
pen and you count them out, and the tenth one is מעשר
בהמה. Maiser Beheima Okay, so let's say now but you need ten
to have מעשר. ma'aser Let's say you had five sheep, five new
sheep and five new calves. You don't put them all together and
count out ten. Okay, you have to you do them separately, which
actually is a leniency, right? Because it means that if there's any
number less than, you know, less than divisible by ten, you don't
have to give from, whereas as opposed to, you know, collecting all
the remainders and giving again. But it also means you can't give
a sheep for a cattle. That if you have ten cattle, you
have to give a calf, you can't give a sheep. Okay, ואין
מתעשרין מזה על זה, so you can't take מעשר ma'aser from flock
to the to the cattle.
Now, בכבשים ובעזים, bichvasim u've'izim, how about different types of flock? When
it comes to sheep and goats? That is,
I'm sorry, it applies to sheep and
to goats, בכבשים ובעזים ומתעשרין מזה על זה, bichvasim u've'izim umisasrin mizeh
al zeh, you take from sheep to goats. So you actually put
all of your sheep and goats, your new sheep and goats, into
one pen and you count them all out. Okay, and you can
take a sheep if you have nine goats and one sheep, and
the sheep happens to be the one that walks out tenth, you
can take for a sheep on the goats or for a goat
on the sheep. Okay, those are considered flock is considered one unit.
Okay,
so you count it out every at the end of each year.
You can wait a few months till you do the counting, we'll
talk about that in a minute. And then the only obligation is
once you've sanctified it, then it only becomes like any other normal
קרבן korban which is defined by the prohibitions of בל תאחר. bal
te'acher. That once something is sanctified as a קרבן, korban, you can't
postpone bringing it more than a year, three רגלים regalim and so
on. But you have time. You certainly can wait before you count
them out. Once you so you if they were I had my
whole new flock from last ראש חודש אלול, Elul maybe I'm supposed
to do it as soon as possible, but I wait a year
or two, as long as I remember which ones were born last,
you know, during the 1999, I put all of them in a
pen and I count them out. But that's not ideal, obviously ideally
it should be soon after they're born.
That would be true and then you'd have to take those each
year you take separately and we're about to get to that. Each
year you go you put all the animals that were born each
year separately and you count them out, which is why ideally you're
supposed to do it right after they're born. But if you delayed,
you can do it later as well. Yes.
Well, branding would be making a מום. mum Could you brand them
before you counted them? Yes.
You know, everyone the same brand when they're born.
Yeah, but then you make a מום, mum, but we'll talk about
that in a minute. But that would be a way for you
to remember, yeah. But then that would be an איסור issur of
a מום, mum but actually we'll get to that because they're not
yet sanctified before you've counted them. So the גמרא Gemara is actually
going to suggest that in a little while as a possible advice.
What do you do nowadays since you can't bring them, why not
just make a מום mum, before they're all before you even count
them? Okay, so that actually yes. Let's keep on going.
Okay,
now, ומתעשרין מזה על זה בחדש ובישן, umisasrin mizeh al zeh bachadash
u'v'yashan, now this is Joe's question, it applies to the newly born
calves and sheep and to the old ones. You're supposed to do
it sort of as I said, you know, soon after they're born,
with the ראש חודש אלול, sometime in אלול would be the normal
time to do it, but let's say you're lazy and you procrastinate,
and it's now a year later, and now you had a whole
new flock that were born. So fine, you still have to take
from last year's, from 2010 and whatever, תש"ע"א, Tashan Ayin Aleph, and
you take from תש"ע"ב, Tashan Ayin Bet, and you take each one
separately. So you have to even if you've waited a year, you
take on the old stuff and you take on the newly born
stuff. That applies to old and to the new.
But ואינם מתעשרין מזה על זה. ve'einam misasrin mizeh al zeh. You
can't take from the flock of
תש"ע"ב Tashan Ayin Bet and for מעשר ma'aser on תש"ע"א. Tashan Ayin
Aleph. Okay, so again, you don't put them all together, which also
means that the rounding, not the error, the remainder, right? If last
year was 23 and this year was 37, you're going to be
giving two and three. You're not going to be giving six. If
you combined them you'd have 60. So you save yourself the remainder
of ten. But it also means that you can't get away by
giving a baby sheep for a one and a half year old
sheep. Okay, right? They have to be separate and you can only
give from תש"ע"א Tashan Ayin Aleph you take one out of every
ten and תש"ע"ב Tashan Ayin Bet you take out of one out
of every ten. Okay, so that's ומתעשרין ואינם מתעשרין מזה על זה.
umisasrin ve'einam misasrin mizeh al zeh. שהיה בדין, Shehaya badin,
now by the way, this is very interesting when the משניות Mishnayot
decide to engage in a little of
מדרש הלכה. Midrash Halacha. actually
you could have made a logical argument to say that you could
take from one year to the next. Why?
You could have made a logical argument to say, excuse me, that
you could take from from cattle or a minute,
I'm sorry, no, the opposite way. The גמרא Gemara. is going to
say why. You could have made an argument to say that you're
not allowed to take from sheep to goats or goats to sheep.
We said you're allowed to take from sheep to goats. You could
have made an argument not. What would have been the argument? ומה
אם החדש והישן
שאינם כלאיים זה בזה u-mah im ha-chadash ve-ha-yashan she-einam kilayim zeh ba-zeh
last year's sheep and this year's sheep are not כלאיים. kilayim. You're
allowed to crossbreed them. There's no, they're basically the same thing. They're
sheep. אינם מתעשרין מזה על זה einam mitasrin mizeh al zeh and
nevertheless you can't take from last year to this year and vice
versa. כבשים ועזים שהן כלאיים זה בזה kvashim ve-izim she-hen kilayim zeh
ba-zeh
goats and sheep which are prohibited to crossbreed, they're fundamentally separate species
of animals, right? אינו דין שלא מתעשרין מזה על זה eino din
she-lo mitasrin mizeh al zeh how much more so should you not
have to, how much more so should you not be able to
take from one to the other? They're fundamentally separate things. It's like
apples and oranges. It's a classic apples and oranges. So since which
is what it has to say, that since fundamentally they're recognized in
many other areas of הלכה, halacha, we never just say generic flock.
Sheep and goat are very distinct categories. So how could you take
from one category to the next? It's apples and oranges. תלמוד לומר
וצאן talmud lomar ve-tzon no, here it says מעשר בקר וצאן ma'asar
bakar ve-tzon here it just uses the generic flock and since it's
using the generic flock for purposes of מעשר בהמה, Maiser Beheima they're
treated as one category.
מכל צאנך mi-kol tzonecha we're treating all flock as one. So yes,
normally you can't take from one type of object on another and
from one year on another, but here for purposes of מעשר בהמה
Ma'aser Behema, flock is one category.
So the hair that comes through, based upon this, the hair that
comes from a goat and what comes from a sheep are both
wool?
No. No, it's not making a larger statement than purposes of מעשר
בהמה. Ma'aser Behema It's actually making the exact opposite statement. What it's
actually saying is that although in all other areas of הלכה halacha
we are normally, consider these very separate categories, here they, and therefore
logically you would have said one you can't take מעשר ma'aser of
the other, here for purposes of מעשר ma'aser the תורה Torah is
treating them as one category.
Yeah exactly, everything's essentially essentially the same as they're the same.
Okay,
I think it makes a lot of sense. It's basically a כלאיים
kilayim
is a חוק chok anyway. You never learn from.
Doesn't matter. They're different categories. Fine, Michael, let's move on. Okay, לימא
leima you'll see in the גמרא Gemara you can't take from wheat
to barley and barley to wheat, okay? So basically מעשר ma'aser fundamentally
acknowledges different categories. Moving on. לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי עקיבא leima masnisin
de-lo ke-rabbi Akiva let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara Let's
say our משנה is not like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Why? דתניא
de-tanya we learned in a ברייתא braisa רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva
omer יכול יעלה אדם מעשר בהמה מחוץ לארץ yachol ya'aleh adam ma'asar
behema mi-chutz la-aretz so
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says maybe you have an, maybe you can
bring your מעשר בהמה maaser behemah. from outside of Israel, from you
know, from Manhattan, from Riverdale and ויקריבנו ve-yakrivenu and you should bring
it as a קרבן, korban, assuming there's a
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. תלמוד לומר והבאתם שמה עולותיכם וזבחיכם ואת מעשרותיכם
talmud lomar va-havasatem shamma olosiechem ve-zivcheichem ve-es masroseichem you shall bring there
to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. your עולות olos and your sacrifices,
your שלמים, shelamim, your and your מעשר. Maiser Now what is מעשר
Maiser do you bring in the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? Meaning normally
מעשר Maiser you give to the עני ani or you give it
to the לוי Levi and they eat it wherever they eat it.
So there's one מעשר Maiser, of grain you do bring into the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. which is מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. You don't
eat it in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash whatever, you bring it
to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, so that's מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. What other,
so that's one thing, but it says מעשרותיכם masroseichem in the plural.
So it says בשתי מעשרות הכתוב מדבר bi-shtei masros ha-kasuv medaber the
text mentions two types of מעשרות. masros. אחד מעשר בהמה ואחד מעשר
דגן echad ma'asar behema ve-echad ma'asar dagan whether it's both מעשר Maiser
of animals and מעשר Maiser, of grain, meaning that מעשר שני. ma'aser
sheni. Those are the only two מעשרות masros that you would bring
to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So ממקום mi-makom and therefore רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says now that that's the פשט pshat in the פסוק, pasuk, let's
learn something else out from that. ממקום שאתה מעלה מעשר דגן אתה
מעלה מעשר בהמה mi-makom she-atah ma'aleh ma'asar dagan atah ma'aleh ma'asar behema
where you bring your grain from, ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael. is where
you bring your מעשר Maiser of animals. וממקום שאין אתה מעלה מעשר
דגן אין אתה מעלה מעשר בהמה u-mi-makom she-ein atah ma'aleh ma'asar dagan
ein atah ma'aleh ma'asar behema where you don't bring your grain is
from, out of Israel, you don't bring your מעשר Maiser of animals.
So although it's true that normally we say it's agricultural מצוות mitzvos
that are limited to the land of Israel, this is actually quite
interesting if you think about it conceptually because it is true that
the animals don't grow from the land of, I mean they graze
from the field but I don't think that's the point. I think
the point is why do we think that you know agricultural מצוות
mitzvos are limited to the land of Israel? So one is to
define it in very metaphysical slash הלכה halacha terms, that there's like
קדושה kedusha, in the land and the קדושה kedusha, sort of you
know is imbued in the you know or transfers into the grain
that grows and that has קדושה kedusha and therefore you take it
and that explains why it's only for grain that grows in Israel.
If that were true, unless you want to talk about the קדושה
kedusha of the of the grass being digested by the animals that
are grazing, it's very hard to imagine why you would think to
put animals in the same category. But there's another way about thinking
about it and the way about thinking about it is that the
תורה Torah imagines that the Jewish polity you know sort of political
entity you know is the Jewish people living in the land ...of
Israel as a country, as a people, right? And therefore these obligations
about giving תרומות Trumos and מעשרות Maisros are about sort of how
we function as a people in the land of Israel. As such,
the animals that are being raised are also part of the agricultural
reality of us as a people, meaning as opposed to grain I'm
growing in, you know, in Ohio, in Iowa, or animals I'm grazing,
you know, somewhere, you know, in France, or whatever it might be,
you know, fine, that's, you know, my own personal even like a
Jewish community that might be there, but it is not sort of
the agriculture of the country, it's not how we're operating as a
country. And I think that's sort of the logic here, meaning the
why because the מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah is, you know, it's very
much the idea every single year, the agricultural, what I'm also trying
to say is that the agriculture as a the central economy of
the country, you know, in that way מעשר Ma'aser. is the animals
is very linked to the idea of of the מעשר Ma'aser of
the grain. What is the central economy of an agricultural society? It's
the grain and it's the animals. Okay, so as such, you know,
that's sort of why that's the sort of I think what's sort
of informing this idea, that the reason that מעשר Ma'aser here is
given, you know, as part of the what what the country, you
know, what we as the people are producing, you know, every single
year, and it's in that context. And therefore רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
is saying that it doesn't apply outside the land of ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. Yes.
But רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva lived before the destruction of the temple.
No, he did not. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was the was persecuted
in the Hadrianic persecution around 130. But he was there during the
destruction.
Maybe, I don't know, how old was he? Ten? Maybe. Yeah. Okay,
I mean I don't know the exact years, but I'm
saying we would have noticed massive numbers of animals coming from בבל
Bavel or Italy had we actually brought and I've never seen any
reference.
Well, that's
a fascinating question and maybe that also maybe that
informed רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position. Maybe
he, you know, or if not even if he didn't actually directly
witness it, maybe, you know, since he overlaps with that generation, maybe
he said, you know, we've never heard of people having brought it
from חוצה לארץ. Chutza La'aretz, Now, right, now part of the problem
is is that you never know what to do with that information
because most of the diaspora communities were not so frum, you know,
so and even if they, you know, obviously strongly identified as Jewish,
right, so the thing is that definitely was a major בבל Bavel
community. Okay, but again, מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah. could be brought at
any given time. So how would you know if somebody is bringing
a קרבן korban from בבל, Bavel, is a visitor from בבל, Bavel,
how much is it a where I guess you would be aware
because it's not there'd be a lot of animals.
Right, it'd be a lot of animals.
Right. But it does it raises an important question about how what
how many Jews were observant in the rabbinic mindset, although this is
of course a פסוק Pasuk that you want to prove something about
the way the rabbi, the way the rabbinic, you know, what's understood
as the תורה שבעל פה Torah Sheba'al Peh about this. How many
Jews were observant in the rabbinic mold,
particularly outside of Israel at the time of the late first and
the second בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash So it's an interesting question why
you didn't actually bring evidence, but I I think that there's a
reason why the, you know, the evidence would have been questionable. Okay,
but that's a very interesting point.
Yeah, so what you were saying, because, you know, what we could
have done is and this is a very גמרא-ish Gemara thing to
do, which is why I'm saying it, is okay, now that it's
all in the פסוק, Pasuk, the היקש Heikesh of the עולה Olah
to the מעשר, Ma'aser just like according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
you can't bring a מעשר maaser from חוצה לארץ, so if I
want to be מקיש Makish my בהמה Beheima as an עולה, Olah,
I shouldn't be able to do that. Okay, but see, yeah, I
think this is what you were saying, maybe is that you can't
make that substitution somehow, just flesh it out a little bit more,
that somehow it's particularly מעשר בהמה's Maaser Behemah, linked to the as
a person.
Yes, what I'm saying is, first of all, well two things. First
of all, מעשרותיכם Maisroseichem are literally in the same word. So first
of all, I think that to answer that's an easier point. מעשרותיכם
Maisroseichem are literally in the same word. And right, we've never the
idea but I guess you're right to some degree it does go
back to what I'm saying, meaning that's just a technical answer. But
the idea of an עולה, Olah, you know, I mean my God,
the נביא Navi talk about the about non-Jews from all over bringing
their קרבנות. Korbanot. שלמה המלך Shlomo Hamelech when he dedicates the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash. says wherever people will be. So it's very clear
you bring קרבנות Korbanot. from wherever. So we're not going to read
the פסוק Pasuk that way. No, we're not going to read the
פסוק Pasuk that way. The idea anybody can come and be in
בית השם Beis Hashem and bring a קרבן. korban But the idea
of מעשר, maaser if you if your idea as the reason you
give מעשר maaser? is somehow the sanctity transferring to the grain, then
it's irrelevant to the idea of בהמה. Beheima. But if the idea
is is that this is your annual agricultural, which is the main
economy, the produce of your
each year of your main economy of the agriculture, so included in
an agricultural society is the animals and the grain. And that's what
they bring. Now, if your focus is on that as an individual,
so fine, so you can also bring it from Newark and you
can also but that would be true about the grain as well.
But no, the focus is on us as a country. And that's
what I think is רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva argument. I think it's
a very fascinating way of thinking about the whole idea of מעשר
maaser, and its connection to ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael, Is it considered a tax?
No. What do you mean a tax? No. I mean sometimes you'll
say that the idea of giving מעשר לוי Maiser Levi is because
of the... חלף עבודתם אשר הם עובדים, chelef avodatam asher hem ovdim,
which is what the תורה Torah says, in exchange for their service.
So the מעשר לוי Ma'aser Levi has maybe some of that element.
But this is brought as a קרבן korban. to God, and מעשר
שני Ma'aser Sheni also you eat in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So it's, you
know, מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni
is the closest thing to it.
Yeah, and that's discussed in מסכת שקלים, Masechet Shekalim, and they levied
additional... Right, מסכת שקלים, Masechet Shekalim, yeah.
But that, yeah, that was more of a tax in its implementation,
not in its purpose, but I guess you could say that about
all taxes, to serve communal good.
In מסכת שקלים Masechet Shekalim there were additional taxes that were paid
at the same time.
Right. Okay, so anyway moving on,
right. So, so it says like this,
so you see, so it's against רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva because רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you do not bring it, fine, מה
שאין כן במעשר דגן ומה שאין כן במעשר בהמה. ma she'ein ken
bema'aser dagan u'ma she'ein ken bema'aser behema. אפילו תימא רבי עקיבא. afilu
teima Rabbi Akiva. No, it could even be
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. כאן להקריב כאן לקדש. kan lehakriv kan lekadesh.
That it's a difference, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you cannot bring
it and you know, to, you don't bring it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim
So maybe all he's saying is that it cannot actually be offered
from חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. If you, but it still has קדושה,
kedusha which is the worst of both worlds, right? Worst of both
worlds, which is out of ירושלים Yerushalayim, you have to count each
tenth animal and sanctify it, but because it's not from ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, you count each tenth animal and sanctify it, but because
it's not coming from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael. it doesn't have enough
sanctity to actually be brought as a קרבן. korban. So now you're
stuck, you have to wait till it gets a מום and eat
it outside of ירושלים, but it's like what's the point if you're,
if it not even has the potential of being brought as a
קרבן? korban. But that's how the גמרא Gemara tries to reconcile our
משנה with רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, although it makes it a less
compelling position that way. Okay, it's interesting to understand what the logic
of that middle position is. Okay, so כאן להקריב, kan lehakriv, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you don't bring
it, כאן לקדש, kan lekadesh, but sanctifying maybe you do, and that's
our משנה. דיוקא נמי דקתני והבאתם שמה. diyuka nami dekatani vahavatem shama.
And that also is inferred by the language because he quotes the
verse of 'you shall bring there' your עולות, olot, meaning referred to
bringing it as a קרבן, korban not the question about whether they
are sanctified. Okay, I mean you could also have emphasized
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva phrase, יכול יעלה אדם ויקריבנו. yakhol ya'aleh adam
veyakrivenu. I would have emphasized that more than the פסוק, pasuk, that
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says perhaps you could offer it up as
a קרבן. korban So maybe he's only rejecting bringing it as a
קרבן korban. but not rejecting the idea that it's sanctified.
שמע מינה. shema mina. So then the גמרא Gemara. says that's a
good point. אי הכי מאי שאינו קרב ומאי קדוש? ei hakhi mai
she'eino karev u'mai kadosh? So then the גמרא Gemara says so what's
the whole point, why is it sanctified if you're never going to
be able to bring it as a קרבן korban, from out of
Israel? למאכל במומו לבעלים. lema'achal bemumo liva'alim. No, it still has halakhic
relevance. As I said, it has קדושה, kedusha you can't do anything
with it until it gets a מום, and once it gets a
מום then what you're allowed to do is שחט shecht it and
eat it. So there's relevance to the קדושה kedusha in that it
restricts you. You don't bring it as a קרבן, korban, but it
restricts you until it gets a blemish. Of course it's very nice
that it has relevance, but what's the point of it? Meaning why
would the תורה have demanded, you know, again unless you sort of
somehow say that there's sort of both of those elements. That the
idea, you know, the idea that we had before רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva assumed that it wasn't tied to the land of Israel, right?
So the idea that it was a personal obligation, that that's true,
but the fact that the way in which it's brought, meaning you
could try to say that. The personal sense of having to give
thanks to God
for what I've earned this year, the general concept of מעשר. maaser.
The way that gets translated at the time of the ראשונים, Rishonim,
which a) they didn't have agricultural society and b) they weren't living
in the land of Israel. So how does the idea of מעשר
maaser. get translated? It gets translated into a concept of מעשר כספים,
Ma'aser Kesafim, that you give a tenth of your earnings each year.
So that is focusing, that takes this idea which is about agriculture
and about Israel and translating it and saying, hey, we have to,
you know, embrace this religious concept of מעשר maaser, even as individuals,
even not as a country, a people living in the land of
Israel. And that's obviously a very powerful idea that you acknowledge God's
hand and that you give a מעשר maaser, and so on. So
maybe what we're saying here is that you have both elements by
מעשר maaser? בהמה, the individual element which isn't linked to the country
and the people in the country and isn't linked to the land
of Israel, that's still there and therefore you have to sanctify each
tenth thing. But the concept that you then bring it as a
קרבן, that maybe is connected specifically to what it means to be
part of a people living in Israel and bringing it to the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So that's a way I would suggest of
explaining this very, you know, challenging middle position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that you sanctify it out of Israel but you don't bring
it as a קרבן out of Israel. I see that there are
a lot of hands. Yes, Joe.
But מעשר maaser בהמה doesn't get given to a כהן. Kohen. It's
you, you bring it and you eat it. Right. But it's still
more like מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni.
Yes, it is in that way, yes.
So it doesn't translate to מעשר...
maaser, No, no, no, I still don't agree because the idea of
acknowledging God doesn't mean that some כהן Kohen has to benefit. Meaning
the way we think about מעשר כספים Ma'aser Kesafim is we give
it to the poor. And obviously there's a very important social and
religious purpose served by that. But the first step is not what
you do
with
it. a tenth to God. Now how does giving it to God
translate, right? Does it translate to giving it to the כהנים, Kohanim,
does it translate to giving it to the poor? Maybe it translates
as eating it in the presence of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash
in the presence of God, where there that you physically benefit from
it, but it's still an acknowledgment of what God has given you.
So that the question about what's done with it is just how
do you translate that idea of giving to God, which should have
many translations. And I think that, you know, the idea of eating
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, is very powerful if the idea
is acknowledging sort of, you know, what God has done. Yes.
It was actually יעקב Yaakov
who said that
I will give, I will give a tenth of everything.
It's really real to me, I will give a tenth.
Right. And it started a little bit by אברהם Avraham in one
episode
where he takes the where he conquered סדום ועמורה, Sodom v'Amorah, I
mean he conquered the countries that fought against סדום ועמורה Sodom v'Amorah
and he takes all their wealth, anyway, and then he and then
he and then he goes ahead and he gives a tenth to
מלכי צדק Malki Tzedek of all of the booty that he captured.
Right. And there you see exactly in those cases that it has
nothing to do with, you know, not nothing, but it's not limited
to the concept
of the קדושה kedusha of Israel and of the grain, it's a
much larger concept of gratitude and acknowledging God.
Do we take on anything from אברהם Avraham and יעקב? Yaakov?
Well yes, the concept of מעשר כספים, Maaser Kesafim, of giving a
tenth of our
income, is modeled after, it's not sort of, really is a מנהג,
minhag, although some ראשונים, Rishonim, some פוסקים Poskim think it's biblical or
it's rabbinic, most it's understood that it's a מנהג, minhag, a custom.
But a custom that basically is modeled after what אברהם Avraham did,
what יעקב Yaakov did, sort of the clear religious value is expressive
and the religious value is there in the מעשר maaser. of the
grain as well and the מעשר maaser בהמה. It's just that the
הלכה halacha doesn't extend that far. So we basically the מנהג, minhag,
the practice of מעשר כספים Maaser Kesafim takes those religious values and
that model and embraces it in practice. And that's what מעשר כספים
Maaser Kesafim is.
And it's a very practical question. So if it's נוהג at all
times, then how do you get out of it today?
Well, that's the next point of the גמרא. Gemara, So let's take
a look. Okay, so did you have a question? That was that.
Okay fine. All right. So now we have a very nice little
introduction about this whole concept of מעשר ma'aser? and the sense of,
you know, as an individual versus as a country.
And I think the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva idea of, you know,
the possibility the גמרא Gemara raises to get out of a problem,
you know, it's interesting the possibility that both elements might be there.
Okay, now we go on. בפני הבית ושלא בפני הבית, whether there
is or is not a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash again you can't
bring it as a קרבן but then you have to deal with
it, it has קדושה kedusha, until it gets a blemish and then
you eat it. אי הכי Ei hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, exactly
as Michael was going to say, right, אפילו האידנא נמי, afilu idna
nami,
so even nowadays why don't we do מעשר? ma'aser So the גמרא
gemara says כרב הונא, k'Rav Huna, like רב הונא Rav Huna says.
דאמר רב הונא, D'amar Rav Huna, גזירה משום יתום. gezeirah mishum yasom.
Now this he says by a different case, but in his particular
case he says we're concerned that sometimes there'll be animals that cannot
be מעשר, ma'aser like what? A יתום. yasom. יתום Yasom is a
very special case I've discussed before where the animal is born at
the moment the mother dies. And interestingly that cannot be brought as
a קרבן.
Just the mother, not the father.
The mother, right, because it's based on the פסוק pasuk of שבעת
ימים יהיה תחת אמו. shivas yamim yihiyeh tachas imo. So if there
was no moment it was תחת אמו, tachas imo, where its mother
was alive after it was born, it cannot be brought as a
קרבן. Now there are other animals that also cannot be not only
cannot be brought, doesn't get sanctified with the קדושה kedusha, of מעשר.
ma'aser? For example, with a blemish as we know, a blemish does
not prevent the קדושה kedusha of מעשר. ma'aser So actually if and
not only does it not prevent if it comes after, even if
it was there before. So you're counting out your animals and the
tenth one had a blemish, has a missing leg, it still has
the קדושה kedusha of מעשר, Maaser. it just means you eat it
out of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So a blemish does not
prevent the קדושה, kedusha, but there are a number of problems with
animals that do prevent it even from becoming קדוש. kadosh. One is
the case of the orphan, the other is orphan from the mother,
the other is for example crossbreed, a כלאים, kilayim, or a טריפה,
treifah, or a יוצא דופן, yotzei dofen, an animal that was cesarean
section. All of those would not even become קדוש. kadosh. So יתום
yasom here represents what
happens if they were the tenth.
That's what I'm about to say. So the יתום yasom here represents
the class of things that would not be קדוש. kadosh. And what
are you supposed to do? So you're supposed to take all those
out of your flock before you start the counting because those are
not part of the they're not even the potential. But if you
don't know the הלכה halacha and you don't take those out of
your flock and it becomes the tenth, you'll think that this has
קדושת מעשר kedushas maaser and it does not. So and the גמרא,
gemara תוספות Tosafot says maybe we're particularly emphasizing יתום yasom because it's
a very obscure הלכה halacha and it's not physically obvious and therefore
we're afraid that people will make that mistake. Now what's the big
Yeah, but the big deal is is that you'll treat this as
it has קדושת מעשר, kedushat maaser, which really it's the next one,
every single will get thrown off, right? So it's not just you'll
treat this with greater stringency, it's that the next one is supposed
to be מעשר, Maaser everything gets messed up. Okay, so therefore we're
afraid of those scenarios and therefore we say what? Don't do it
in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. Now, or don't do it nowadays that
there's no בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash? Now, the next obvious question, the
first most obvious question is, don't do it, what do you mean?
So I count them but I eat it even though I've sanctified
it as מעשר? Maaser No, no, there's an easier answer here. Because
here, unless you do this process of counting them, nothing gets the
קדושת מעשר. kedushat maaser. And unlike grain, if I don't take תרומה
ומעשר trumah u'maaser from my grain, it's טבל tevel and it's forbidden
to be eaten. Unlike grain, if I don't do מעשר for my
animals, it's not forbidden, I can eat my animals. I've transgressed the
מצוה mitzvah of giving מעשר, but I haven't eaten something that is
forbidden meat. Okay, so therefore what we're saying of not to do
it nowadays is the Rabbis are telling us שב ואל תעשה. shev
v'al ta'aseh. Don't do the biblical מצוה mitzvah of counting it out.
And therefore nothing will get the קדושה, kedusha, and therefore you won't
have to deal with making these mistakes and all of the consequences
that derive from it. So don't do the מצוה mitzvah of counting
out מעשר. That's their answer. Now, the next question is, I know,
now the next question is that well, why weren't we concerned about
that when there was the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash I mean, why
wouldn't these problems apply? Exactly. So we'll take a look at it.
What were you saying, Rivka?
Oh, they just wrote out the מצוה, mitzvah, they didn't want...
Right, but because they didn't want because it was right, the implications
were having to deal with קדושה kedusha. nowadays and all those implications,
it was much, there was the logic
of the Rabbis to suggest שב ואל תעשה.
shev v'al ta'aseh. Exactly. Exactly, particularly in this case where it's basically
about, as Michael says, שב ואל תעשה, shev v'al ta'aseh, sit and
don't do.
And then you could imagine someone comes now, you now have this
bull sitting and thinks he wants to be מעשר ומום הוא ידור.
maaser u'mum hu yador.
We're getting there. All right, we're not done. We're not
done. שקט
בבקשה. sheket bevakasha. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says, no,
no, so
why don't we go back to the time, let's say you have
a flock and somehow you're not looking carefully enough and you miss
the four guys who has this thing and you start counting, then
you make this mistake, what happens then? What happens?
Well, that
so we can talk about that, it's interesting because then what happens
if then after he was ten, you did the next one and
you said one, I mean really should have said ten, does that
mean that he's קדוש kadosh or not קדוש? kadosh? So some of
that we'll talk to when we get to our פרק. Let's hold
that off for now. So the גמרא gemara says anyway, clearly it
would create problems. So the גמרא gemara says אי הכי, ee hachi,
the next obvious question is, מעיקרא נמי לא, me-eikar nami lo,
so if that's so such a big concern, don't do it when
there is a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash How'd you ever let anybody
do it? אלא אפשר דמכרזא, ella efshar d'machraza, what's the answer to
that? Teach people. Meaning, since when is the answer to ignorance, to
ignorance, accepting the ignorance and no, the answer to ignorance is
education, not try to make other things to accept ignorance. You don't
accept ignorance, you educate. So הכא נמי אפשר דמכרזא. hacha nami efshar
d'machraza. Here too let's announce it and let's educate people. As long
as people are practicing it, so they'll want to be educated about
it. So let's announce it and let's educate them. אלא אמר רבא
משום תקלה. ella amar Rava mishum takala.
No, you're right. The problem isn't the mistake, the problem is a
stumbling block. What's a stumbling block? The very fact that what do
you do with things that have קדושה kedusha nowadays? In the time
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash it had קדושה, kedusha you could
deal with it immediately. You'd either bring it to the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash? or if it had a מום, you'd eat it out
of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash Chic-chac. Nowadays it's got קדושה, kedusha?
it doesn't have a blemish, you gotta wait years and years and
years, and there obviously is going to lead to cases
of transgression, of misusing the animal, of
impinging on the קדושה. kedushah, And therefore because that it creates an
obviously stumbling block we'd rather not deal with it. The downside of
dealing with קדושה kedushah of מעשר and having them stay around for
forever before you're able to do something is too great and we'd
rather just put it aside. Yes.
Why can't we just sell the ear of every animal?
So the גמרא Gemara is getting to all that. Let's keep on
going. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ומינה תימא דחיישינן לתקלה, u'minah
teima d'chayshinan l'takala,
how do I know I'm concerned about stumbling
blocks? That I would sort of
prefer not to deal with the קדושה kedushah, rather than deal with
its consequences. דתניא, d'tanya, we're taught in a ברייתא, braita, אין מקדישין
ואין מעריכין ואין מחרימין בזמן הזה. ein makdishin v'ein ma'arichin v'ein machrimim
b'zman hazeh. Nowadays don't sanctify things to the בית המקדש. מקדישין, makdishin,
these are different ways in which you create sanctity, but for without
getting into their specific differences, do not sanctify objects to the בית
המקדש nowadays. Not good advice. ואם הקדיש והעריך והחרים, v'im hikdish v'heerich
v'hecherim, if you went ahead and did it, what are you gonna
do with this object that has sanctity, קדושה? kedushah You can't give
it to any בית המקדש, you can't use it, if you misuse
it by accident you've transgressed מעילה, me-ila, misuse of
הקדש hekdesh and objects. So better to get rid of the problem
than to have it around waiting to be a stumbling block and
a source of sin. So ומה נעשה לו? v'mah na'aseh lo? No,
well, that's far, we can't say, we're not going, so let's take
a look. So he says, ואם v'im if you did it, now
I know I'm going to get a lot of response from the
next words I'm about to read: בהמה תעקר, beheimah t'aker, an animal
you have to make sterile, which the גמרא Gemara is going to
say doesn't mean even mean make sterile, it really means you let
it die, you lock it in a room and you let it
die. פירות כסות וכלים ירקבו, peiros kesus v'keilim yerakevu, any other thing,
things like fruit and objects that decompose, you lock them up in
some storage and you let them rot and decompose. מעות וכלי מתכות,
maos u'klei masachos, money and metal, which is going to be around
for forever, right? What do you do with those things? How do
you prevent things for people from them being misused? יוליך לים המלח,
yolich l'yam hamelach, you throw them into the Dead Sea, you grind
them up maybe as תוספות Tosafot speaks about throwing into other bodies
of water, and basically you have to get rid of these objects.
Now, of course you'll say, isn't that itself a violation? Interestingly, number
one is that the prohibition of מעילה me'ilah is misusing הקדש, hekdesh,
not destroying הקדש. hekdesh. Now, while that might be true, isn't it
the problem? I mean, at least it's גזל, gezel, it's destroying something
that's הקדש. hekdesh. But the point is that הקדש hekdesh can't benefit
from it anyway nowadays, so therefore since there will actually be no
accrued benefit—of course it says במהרה יבנה בית המקדש bimherah yibaneh beis
hamikdash and then whatever—but since anyway there's no practical way right now
that הקדש hekdesh can benefit, it's actually not seen as a prohibition
to destroy these things. Now, what remains obviously a major question about
this is, and is that, you know, you're allowed to transfer קדושה,
kedushah. if it's קדושת בדק הבית, kedushas bedek habayis, to money of
even a lesser value. שמואל Shmuel says הקדש שוה מנה שחיללו על
שוה פרוטה מחולל. hekdesh shaveh maneh shechilelo al shaveh perutah mechulal. If
something is worth $10,000 and you transfer the קדושה kedushah to a
penny, it actually transfers. Now, you're not allowed to do it because
you're stealing from הקדש, hekdesh, but nowadays since הקדש hekdesh isn't losing,
you would be allowed to do it. So it doesn't explain why,
now maybe you could say, well, we want to punish you, what
you did was so irresponsible we don't want to let you get
away with only like losing a dollar, we want to actually teach
you a lesson and teach maybe the community a lesson and demonstrate
that you're going to throw this away, you're going to let it
rot. That's all very nice for inanimate objects. It doesn't really help
so much for the case of the animal, which we are letting
starve to death, which we will now read explicitly. So let's take
a look. ואיזו עיקור? v'eizo ikur? One minute, what does it mean
to sterilize the animal? נועל דלת בפניה והיא מתה מאליה. noel deles
befaneha v'hi mesah me'ileha. You lock the door in a room and
you let it die. So again, this raises serious questions about צער
בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. גמרות Gemaras like this are the source
for a number of ראשונים rishonim to say that צער בעלי חיים,
tza'ar ba'alei chayim, when it serves religious or even human purposes, is
justified, because here apparently the rabbis understand that for the sake of
teaching you and teaching the community a lesson about the irresponsibility of
doing this—that's the best way I understand it, because or else obviously
you have to get rid of the problem, but that you could
have transferred the קדושה, kedushah but therefore we actually demand such drastic
measures. Yes.
Is this transferring is with money as what we do in Israel
with
מעשר?
Yes, that's פדיון מעשר. pidyon ma'aser. Yes, exactly.
But don't, doesn't that coin get filled up, as opposed to the
study you mentioned about it can be as big an amount as
you want?
Yes, but each time we transfer מעשר שני ma'aser sheini in Israel
to a coin, you have to transfer it on a פרוטה. perutah.
So eventually you've transferred it a thousand times, the value of that
coin is now filled. So then what you do is—what David is
asking is, this is an interesting application of this, it's a little
digression, but we actually have an idea of applying this of transferring
higher value to lesser value nowadays when you take תרומות ומעשרות terumos
u'ma'asros in Israel. What do you do with מעשר שני? ma'aser sheini?
So you transfer the קדושה kedushah? to a coin, but you only
transfer—you might have like $10 worth of מעשר שני—you ma'aser sheini transfer
it to a penny's worth of the coin. But the coin they
tell you actually to get a coin that has intrinsic value, I
don't know, let's say a silver dollar or gold krugerrand, whatever it
is. Once that coin, after a thousand times of transferring a penny's
worth, eventually all of that coin will now be 100 percent have
קדושה. kedushah So they say is you have two coins, and therefore
as soon as that coin gets filled up you transfer the קדושה
kedushah from a coin one—the $10, let's say a $10 krugerrand piece
or whatever, no krugerrands are worth a lot more, anyway, you transfer
that to one penny of the next coin, then you then the
next coin gets filled up and then you transfer it back to
one penny of the other coin and keep on going back, and
it's like a perpetual motion machine. That's how that works. But that
is that principle of, that is that principle that nowadays because הקדש
hekdesh isn't losing out you're allowed to transfer greater value to lesser
value, which raises the question about, like I said, why although you
have to get rid of the stumbling block, why you had to
do, why you had to do it in this way that's so
destructive, presumably the חז"ל Chazal understood that that was important for the
for the larger lesson.
But they do, they do eventually get rid of the coin?
The one that you sanctify to the temple. Now, the question is,
here's the issue about this, one minute, here's the issue. The issue
about this is is that this is talking about sanctifying for the
temple, where there the only concern, minus the concern of animal suffering,
is the is the value of it, and if הקדש hekdesh can't
have any monetary benefit... So you're not really hurting הקדש hekdesh by
destroying it and you have to were concerned about the stumbling. You
cannot say the same about קרבן. By קרבן the sense of the
קדושה kedusha is more than just its value. So to do this
type of a thing right by קרבן especially one which didn't have
a blemish and like in theory could be brought if there was
a בית המקדש would be potentially a different story. So let's take
a look. Okay so that's why for example the גמרא Gemara is
now going to sort of ask essentially the same question by בכור.
bechor By מעשר if this thing is already sanctified you destroy. If
it's מעשר don't do it in the first place. But what about
בכור? bechor Why don't we say take a בכור bechor. and lock
it up in a room and let it die? Is that even
an option? This idea of destroying is an option for things that
are sanctified to the treasury, not necessarily an option by things that
are sanctified as a קרבן. So we are going to take a
look now as we ask the question about בכור. bechor Yes.
Do we really believe that השם Hashem would be really happy with
us taking this beautiful wonderful innocent animal and locking him up? I
know you were waiting for this anyway. I know. Boy, for sure.
Absolutely not. I mean you only do
that when you transgress.
No, but you're
saying why
don't we put ourselves in a room and lock
ourselves up? We transgress, not the animal.
We transgress in holiness and so something is holy, how do you
deal with it? You torture it and make it die. There's a
disconnect. Right. You mean
even besides the animal suffering
issue. Right, that is an excellent point. No, I think that is
an excellent point. What you're saying is even bracketing the animal suffering
issue, which by the way I have to tell you, and not
like I don't share your outrage, but I have to think that
we have to, I think that you know we have to acknowledge
that whatever anybody here who's not a vegetarian, whenever we raise the
animal suffering we're all being hypocrites. The amount of animal suffering that
goes into the current meat industry is enormous. But anyway, but let's
bracket, fine, but let's bracket, let's bracket, let's bracket the animal suffering
issue because what you're saying is even bracketing that, even bracketing that,
if you're taking something sanctified and destroying it, then doesn't that undermine
the whole concept of קדושה? kedusha And you know, I think that's
an excellent point and like I said, there's a better way of
dealing with this. You could transfer it to a penny, you know,
and at least and keep the penny locked up in some room
or something like that. So you know, it raises an important question.
Now they do give an option of transferring it to a penny,
but here they're still concerned about having to, they would at least
here not, and that's a question why didn't they have that option?
And then they would at least say but you might misuse the
penny, so destroy the penny, you know. So the concern of you
know what it reflects and you are correct is the concern of
transgression and the concern of transgression sometimes being, right, because you might
misuse it and transgress מעילה, me'ilah, you know, being an overriding value
against what you're expressing which is the value of
appreciating what קדושה kedusha means and of sort of affirming what קדושה
kedusha. means. So I understand that. What it really reflects is that
very strong concern of transgression, which is the phase of תקלה takalah
which is רבא's Rava point. How can I tell you not to
do the מצוה mitzvah of מעשר? Sometimes we're so concerned about transgression
that other things have to, you know, that it overrides other things.
Yes.
Well this is an example where the תורה שבעל פה Torah Sheba'al
Peh is so important because the rabbis are ordering us, just like
they order us not to sound the שופר shofar on שבת, Shabbos,
even on ראש השנה that falls on שבת. Shabbos. Now they're ordering
us not to perform this מצוה. mitzvah. Right. So we transgress, the
only time we're going to have to lock them up is when
we transgress.
Right, right, I understand. Okay, fine. But even taking your example and
then we're going to move on, not everybody is happy with the
fact that we can't take שופר, shofar, blow שופר shofar or take
לולב. lulav. Right.
But the question are we better Jews or not?
Right, we are, and that's why we do it. But the point
is that giving voice to the sense that there were competing values
here, right? And the rabbis absolutely said that the concern of transgression
sometimes overrides those other values and that's what's being expressed.
Yes. What about the coin
and transferring back and forth? Don't they eventually put it in the
sea nowadays?
Ah, that I don't know.
And also this idea of transgression, they're concerned when they use the
word sterilize, so they don't
literally mean it.
No, but are they concerned if you let it live that it
might reproduce?
That was that's also a concern. The primary concern is misusing the
animal itself, but that's also a concern. Sterilize here is translated as
meaning let it die. Okay, let's let's finish this up. There's been
a lot of fascinating conversation but let's get a little bit further.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, ei hachi,
if that's your concern of misuse, בכור נמי לא יתקדש, bechor nami
lo yitkadesh, so don't sanctify a בכור. bechor So the גמרא Gemara
says excuse me, בכור בידן תליא מילתא, bechor beyadan talya milsa, are
we the ones that sanctify בכור? bechor מרחם קדיש, merachem kadesh, it
becomes sanctified through the womb, it happens automatically. Exactly, we can't control
that. So the גמרא Gemara says, so הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's
the question. Now notice the גמרא Gemara doesn't say let's lock the
בכור bechor in a room. That solution was only for things that
are בדק הבית bedek habayit which were about ownership. Primarily the קדושה
kedusha was about that they were owned and they were property. בכור
bechor which is קדושה kedusha more intrinsic as a קרבן, that suggestion
of locking in a room is not raised. Why not? But there
because for the reason I just said. But there are but there
are but okay well you'll think about it. Okay because it's not
just about הקדש hekdesh losing out its value which isn't a concern
when there's no בית המקדש. Its intrinsic קדושה kedusha. dictates what should
be done with it and to lock it into a room would
undermine the whole nature of its קדושה. kedusha. Fine.
Anyway, shhh.
Okay, focus everybody please. Thank you. All right. So now that we're
dealing with בכור, bechor מעשר don't do, if you say give something
to the treasury since the temple doesn't benefit from it anyway, the
solution can be to destroy it, noting all the points. But at
least there fundamentally the קדושה kedusha is about ownership and value. By
בכור bechor. where the קדושה kedusha is about its its sort of
its purpose to be brought as a קרבן, it is not raised
as a possibility to lock it in a room which would completely
contradict Rifka your point the nature of its קדושה. kedusha. So the
question is not why don't we lock a בכור Bechor, in a
room but if you're so concerned about misuse, there are other solutions
to בכור. Bechor Why don't we say הכי קאמר לקנינהו לאזניהו לעובדי
כוכבים? hachi ka'amar likninehu le-oznaihu le-ovdei kochavim?
Why not sell the ear of the בכור Bechor, of the mother
to a non-Jew and get around ever having to deal nowadays and
the גמרא Gemara we'd get around ever having to deal with בכור
Bechor, דלא יתקדש מעיקרא de-lo yitkadesh me-ikara that it should never have
been sanctified from the beginning. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, there's other solutions. אפשר כדרב יהודה. efshar k'de-Rav Yehuda.
Yes you're right, we are concerned about בכור Bechor, but that's not
what we advise. Here's what we advise. We advise רב יהודה's Rav
Yehuda solution. What's רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda solution? דאמר רב יהודה, de-amar
Rav Yehuda, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says מותר לו לאדם להטיל מום
בבכור קודם שיצא לאויר העולם mutar lo le-adam le-hatil mum bi-bechor kodem
she-yeitzei le-avir ha-olam
that you can make a wound
a blemish in the בכור Bechor before it's born. Basically what you
do is you stick your hand in the womb and you make
a blemish or as it's coming out before the majority of its
head comes out you make a cut in the lip or a
cut in the ear and therefore you make it a blemish. Now
Charlie you've given me a look. Charlie is basically thinking why would
I suggest such a complicated difficult thing rather than the more trivial
and easier thing of selling the ear. And the answer is because
what happens when you sell the ear? You totally prevent it from
becoming קדוש. kadosh. Right? What happens if you make a wound? It
is קדוש. kadosh. But you eat it with the and not only
that who gets it? A בכור with a blemish? כהן. Kohen So
not all so with a with a blemish you are able you're
not concerned about תקלה takala because you're able to deal with it
right away, you שחט it and eat it. You're able to preserve
the concepts of קדושה. kedusha You don't have to do a complete
runaround and you're not preventing the כהן Kohen from getting a week's
worth of steak dinners or lamb chops. Okay? So you're giving so
you're not taking something away from the כהן that he could benefit
from. So the גמרא Gemara believes that by בכור the better solution
is to make a blemish which allows you which avoids the misuse
concern, allows you to retain the concepts of קדושה kedusha, and allows
the כהן to get the בכור. So it says that's why we
don't sell the ear. Now תוספות says of course we do sell
the ear because it's complicated to make this blemish and therefore you
know most of very often we would not be able to do
that.
It's an extra
anyway to make a blemish. Right. Very often we would not be
able to do that successfully and therefore because the גמרא Gemara clearly
expressed the concern of misuse, we actually adopt the solution that the
גמרא Gemara is saying is less ideal but is still a solution
and actually it is to sell the ear and as I told
you when we learned this at the very beginning of the מסכת,
the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch actually says you know
מצוה mitzvah quoting תוספות's idea it's a מצוה mitzvah nowadays to sell
the ear to a non-Jew in order to avoid the concerns of
misuse of תקלה. takala. But for the גמרא Gemara this was a
better solution to make the blemish which had other benefits. Yes.
I'm sorry why is it complicated to
because you have to be there exactly at the moment it's giving
birth. You have to you have to make the blemish before the
majority of the head comes out or you have to stick your
hand into the womb while it's still pregnant and not you know
lead to a miscarriage or whatever. So you know it's not so
trivial. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says yes.
Because what threw me off before was the אימא אקדשי eima akdishi
which I thought to be קדושת הגוף kedushat ha-guf but you're
saying it really
means all קדושת בדק הבית. kedushat bedek ha-bayit.
Well it's also true that you're not מקדיש makdish קדושת הגוף. kedushat
ha-guf. Okay but the question is whether exactly that is the solution
to the קדושת הגוף kedushat ha-guf we're bracketing that for now. Okay.
So anyway the גמרא Gemara says like this הכא נמי אפשר דשדי
ביה מומא מעיקרא. hacha nami efshar de-shadi beih muma me-ikara. So the
גמרא Gemara says okay הכא נמי אפשר דשדי ביה מומא מעיקרא. hacha
nami efshar de-shadi beih muma me-ikara. So here too why do we
basically say don't do the מצוה mitzvah at all, do a complete
runaround? Why don't we say make a blemish and therefore you'll do
the מצוה, mitzvah, you'll preserve the concept of קדושה kedusha, and you'll
remember you'll preserve the מצוה mitzvah and you'll eat it out of
the בית המקדש? So make a blemish beforehand and here actually it's
easier, you don't have to do it before the animal's born. You
just do it before you actually do the counting. Make a blemish
in it and solve the whole problem, and that gets around the
concern. The גמרא Gemara says מי ידע הי נפק? Mi Yadiah Hai
Napak? How do you know which one is going to be 10th?
So what do you mean make a blemish? Which one will be
10th? וכי תימא V'chi Teima fine דאפקה ברישא D'apki Beresha we'll get
there. If you דאפקה
ברישא D'apki Beresha עשרה Asarah you'll, you'll, you know, you'll rig it.
You'll make, you'll make a blemish in one and then you'll make
sure that it comes out number 10. Okay, no, you can't do
that. לא יבקר בין טוב לרע רחמנא. Lo Yevaker Bein Tov L'ra
Rachmana. You can't choose. It has to be random which one comes
out 10th. You're not allowed to, you know, rig, rig the results.
So וכי תימא V'chi Teima אפשר דשדי במומא בכוליה עדרא Efshar Deshadi
Bemuma Bechulei Edra like Michael said, make, let's make a blemish in
every animal. Okay, cut the lip of every single animal, the ear
of every single animal, or suggest brand them. Okay, maybe if you
were going to brand them anyway. Okay, and therefore you solve the
problem. Just do it before the מעשר. So you're able to still
do the מצוה mitzvah of מעשר and you don't have to worry
about misuse. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, here's why we don't
do it. במהרה יבנה בית המקדש. Mehera Yibaneh Beis Hamikdash. God willing,
the בית המקדש will be speedily be
rebuilt ובעינן בהמה להקרבה וליכא. Uvainan Behemah Lehakravah Veleika. And we're going
to need animals without a blemish. Now, if every animal that's born,
because you do this on all the newborn animals, you make blemish,
where are you going to get any animal without a blemish? So
you can't have all our animals blemish. That will undermine, talking about
undermining values, that'll undermine the value that we're looking forward to the
building of the בית המקדש or to the possibility of bringing קרבנות.
Korbanot. Of course it does raise the possibility that you'll buy the
animals from non-Jews. Yeah. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says אפשר
בפשוטים. Efshar Bipsutim. So, outside. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי...
Hacha Nami... Oh, excuse me. So הכא נמי בבכור בהמה. Hacha Nami
Bebechor Behemah. So therefore by בכור, why do we say make a
blemish? Why don't we say, could you turn that off? Why do
we say by בכור make, by בכור, why do we say make
a blemish? Let's say במהרה יבנה בית המקדש ובעינן בהמה להקרבה וליכא.
Mehera Yibaneh Beis Hamikdash Uvainan Behemah Lehakravah Veleika. Why don't we say
that also don't make a blemish in the בכור, right? Which was
the advice we gave you. Because then you won't be able to
use them for, for קרבנות. גמרא Gemara says one minute. אפשר בפשוטים.
Efshar Bipsutim. Our concern is that all of our animals will, will
have blemishes. So what if all the בכורים Bechorim have blemishes? We'll
still have plenty of other animals to bring as קרבנות. So the
גמרא Gemara says okay והכא נמי אפשר בלקוחים. Vehacha Nami Efshar Belikuchim.
You can purchase. Now, if you think that, you might think it
means purchase from non-Jews. No. No,
that's a good point. That's a good point too. Okay, right, when
do we, that's a good point. When would we be concerned about
that? But anyway, the גמרא Gemara here לקוחים likuchim means you're only
obligated to give מעשר בהמה on the animals that are born to
your flock. If I buy Michael's animals before the time of the
year is up, so we both get out of it. He gets
out of it because he doesn't have those animals in his possession
when the year is up, and I get out of it because
they weren't born to my flock. So animals that were purchased, right,
are not obligated in מעשר בהמה. So not every animal will I
have to make a blemish in. So therefore there will still still
be a few animals around that will not have blemishes. So the
גמרא Gemara says no. כיון דאיהו שדי במומא בכוליה עדריה. Keivan De'ihu
Shadi Bemuma Bechulei Edrei.
First of all, since you're making blemishes in all of your flock,
and you probably might make them in all anyway because you don't
know which ones you'll sell. Number one, ושכיחי מומי דפסלי בקדשים דאפילו
דוקין שבעין נמי פסלי. Ushchichi Mumei Depasli Bekodshim De'afilu Dukin Sheba'ayin Nami
Pasli.
And number one, even natural blemishes are, are common, like even a
cataract of the eye, as we've learned a whole פרקא. pirka. So
therefore everything that you're planning that you haven't pre-sold you're going to
make a blemish, there'll be natural blemishes, the number of animals that'll
be left without blemishes will be trivial. So לא שכיחי, lo shchichi,
there's, they'll, you do not want to be in a place where
you where the בית המקדש is rebuilt and only one in a
thousand animals don't have blemishes. So the גמרא's Gemara basic point here
is yes, מעשר applies nowadays, but because we're concerned of misuse of
הקדש, hekdesh, we tell you sit on your תוכס tuchus and don't
count מעשר בהמה, okay, rather than count it and have to deal
with the קדושה. And that we feel is a better solution than
dealing with the קדושה and making blemishes in all the animals. As
opposed to בכור, where at least the גמרא Gemara says deal with
the קדושה, make a blemish before it's born, which A doesn't create
a problem that all your animals have blemishes and B allows you
to retain the concept of קדושה, which was Rivka's concern about the
other thing. So here we're retaining it, although we are making a
blemish, which you could also argue is, you know, is challenging that
concept and we're allowing it to call him together. That's what the
גמרא Gemara said nowadays. But clearly this concern of תקלה, takalah, of
sin was overriding, was overarching. And therefore today nowadays, since that is
seen as a very challenging way of dealing with it, a complicated,
difficult way of dealing with it nowadays the solution to בכור is
what the גמרא Gemara initially suggested, selling the ear of the mother
to a non-Jew and that solves the problems. Two last questions, then
we should...
They made a גזירה gezeirah against raising small animals in ארץ ישראל.
Right. Which would seem to cause exactly these problems.
Yeah, but first of all for first of all you can get
animals from חוץ לארץ, Chutz L'aretz, and remember this this suggestion, solution
would apply to חוץ לארץ Chutz L'aretz as well because it was
an obligation in חוץ לארץ. Chutz L'aretz. And you could raise animals
as long as you weren't doing it in inhabited areas. You, but
you couldn't raise them in inhabited areas. So it's not true that
you couldn't raise animals at all in Israel. Yes.
Is it possible just to distinguish the idea of not doing it
nowadays... because of these possible issues and then what happens if there
is a בית המקדש?
Yes, so the גמרא's Gemara trying to strike that balance. So the
גמרא's striking that balance, so the way the גמרא says it is
that nowadays you don't count your tenth, if the בית המקדש is
rebuilt, we'll start counting the tenth and we have all these animals
without blemishes and then we'll be able to start giving it. Okay,
so to be continued.